A Guide to the Papers of Edwin A. Alderman
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence
  - 1905-1927, n.d. Correspondence: Thomas Fortune Ryan (1851-1928), including thanks to Ryan for providing the Ryan scholarships and asking if he can help support the Medical School (April 3, 1916); telegrams seeking information about Ryan and marriage to his second wife, Mrs. Cornelius C. Cuyler, a prominent society woman of New York, a few weeks after the death of his first wife, which occurred at Holy Comforter Church, Charlottesville, Virginia, on October 29 th with only Alderman and his wife as witnesses (October 29, 1917); Alderman thanks Ryan for his generosity to the University of Virginia during her Centennial endowment campaign and asks if he can persuade some of his friends to support it as well (April 13, 1921)congratulates Alderman on his Wilson speech (December 18, 20,1924); and giving Alderman a car for Christmas and comments on the declining health of Dr. John Staige Davis (December 10, 15, 1927) (Box-folder 5:6)
  - 1893-1930 Correspondence: Sa through Sl, including visiting English student, Christopher V. Salmon; Edward Terry Sanford, Supreme Court Justice (1865-1930) thanking Alderman for his letter of congratulations (June 30, 1923); John R. Saunders (1869-1934), Attorney General of Virginia, inquiring about Alderman's health (April 3, 1923); William Jay Schieffelin; Major General John McAllister Schofield (1831-1906) responding to Alderman's request for a copy of his remarks to the graduating class of West Point cadets by saying that he could not recall them with sufficient accuracy to justify their publication (June 28, 1893); Alderman to Carl Schurz (1829-1906) seeking a meeting with Andrew Carnegie to secure financial assistance in achieving his educational goals at the University of Virginia and in the South in general (January 27, 1905); Frederick W. Scott concerning the death of his wife (December 20, 1930); Alderman to Mrs. Frederick W. Scott concerning the election of her husband as Rector of the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia (April 7, 1930); Alderman to Charles H. Senff requesting a meeting which apparently resulted in a gift to the University of Virginia of $25,000 (January 31, 1909); Davis Sessums (1858-1929) concerning Alderman's decision to leave Tulane University (August 22, 1904); Charles Seymour (1885- ?) asking permission to publish Alderman's note to Colonel House in his edition of House's papers (May 31, 1928); Albert Shaw (1857-1947) sending a printed copy of his speech about Walter Hines Page (March 7, 1924); George Bernard Shaw (1856-1950) explains why he cannot give permission for the University of Virginia to perform one of his plays without charging the usual fees, even to benefit the hospital (March 8, 1912); Mary Shaw concerning genealogy (1924-1925); Edward Fleming Sheffey, Jr.; Edward Morse Shepard (1850-1911); Alderman to Adelaide D. Simpson concerning her resignation as Dean of Women (April 20, 1927); and Thomas Sloo. (Box-folder 5:7)
  - 1895-1930 Correspondence: Sm through Su, including New York Governor Alfred E. Smith (1873-1944) chiefly telegrams and an invitation to speak at the University (1927-1930); Bolton Smith; Chester M. Smith; Duncan Smith concerning his portrait of Woodrow Wilson (April 16 and 18, 1921); Edgar F. Smith (1854-1928); Francis Henry Smith (1829-1928) writing from Honolulu (May 22, 1911), representing the University at the inauguration of the Institute of Technology at Harvard (June 24, 1916) and thanks the Board of Visitors for their greetings on his 90 th birthday (October 17, 1919); Dr. Henry Louis Smith (1859-1951), President of Washington and Lee University, regrets Alderman leaving the University of North Carolina (June 8, 1900); J.H. Smith; Jessica Smith; Joseph D. Smith; Society for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Monticello Branch, concerning the historic grounds of the University, particularly the serpentine walls (October 24, 1907); Fred S. Sorrenson asking permission to use selections from two of his speeches for a volume to be used in high school literary meets (July 3 and 8, 1930); Alderman to Professor C.M. Sparrow (June 19, 1922); Eugene Speicher (1883-?) concerning arrangements to have Alderman's portrait done (1921-1922); Cornelia Phillips Spencer (1825-1908) thanking him for the copy of his Memorial of Signer Hooper (May 13, 1895); Spencer Trask & Company; Eliza Dillon Spilman; James Sprunt; J.C. Squire; Dorothy Stanley; Alderman to Charles M. Steele requesting a donation for the hospital fund (April 4, 1907); Eugene Stevenson (1849-1928) asking if he was interested in the Chancellorship of New York University (September 30, 1910 and January 28, 1911); Matthew W. Stirling about Alderman's election as a charter member of the Geographic and Historical Society of the Americas (February 9 and 11, 1931); Albert A. Stone; Alderman to Ormond Stone concerning Mr. Ryan and philanthropy (October 14, 1908); Robert Strayer; Alderman to Aubrey E. Strode concerning his speech about the need for a women's college (December 7, 1909) and his request for information about Alderman's plans for the University (February 23, 1916); Governor of Virginia, Henry Carter Stuart (1855-1933) concerning Alderman's health and social remarks (May 7, 1914; November 10, 1915; December 26, 1917); Ruth McEnery Stuart (1849-1917) introducing Hugh Chisholm (1866-1924), editor of The Encyclopedia Britannica (January 2, 1902); R.Y Stuart (1883-1933) concerning the development of forestry (April 7, 1927); Harry T. Summersgill (April 24, 1930); W.B. Swaney asking Alderman to encourage Raleigh C. Minor, Professor of Constitutional Law, University of Virginia, to use his book in his law classes (January 28, 1921); and Virginia Governor Claude A. Swanson appointing Alderman to a commission to preserve natural resources (March 18, 1908); congratulates Swanson and the State Board of Education for their very constructive recent educational work (June 28, 1909) (Box-folder 5:8)
  - 1903-1925 Correspondence: Dr. Charles Alphonso Smith (1864-1924) and Mrs. Smith, discusses the impact of the continued influence of Romanticism in the South on its history, including the Civil War, and up to the present (January 30, 1903); congratulates Alderman upon his election as President of the University of Virginia and urges him to accept for the sake of his career and the future of education in the South (June 17, 1904); Alderman lists his work that has been printed and reflects upon his career thus far (June 24, 1909); printed copies of correspondence concerning Smith's resignation as Edgar Allan Poe Professor of English in Alumni Bulletin (April 3, 13, 1917); writes he is unable to help Alderman with an estimate of Woodrow Wilson due to his illness (April 18, May 9, 1924); [Lucie?] M.H. Smith writes Alderman that her husband has an incurable liver disease and is expected to live for only a few weeks or months but is without pain and busy still giving lectures (April 29, May 20, 1924); and Alderman writes concerning the death of Smith (June 14, 1924) (Box-folder 5:9)
  - 1901-1902 Correspondence: Southern Education Board, chiefly Charles D. McIver, but also including one letter from H.S.G. Tucker, concerning the business of the organization, and notes for a talk at the [Philadelphia ?] Conference, November 1, 1902 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - 1919-1922 Correspondence: Southern Railway Company executives, Alderman was a member of the Board of Directors of the Southern Railway, which office Alderman resigned on January 9, 1922 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - 1926 Correspondence: Mark Sullivan (1874-1952), including a copy of a long and detailed letter from Alderman to Sullivan describing his early career and how he got into education and the history of educational change in the South after the devastation of the Civil War (July 3, 1926); Sullivan was writing a history of "Our Times" and asked for Alderman's input on the importance of the revival of education in the South (Box-folder 5:12)
  - 1900-1930 Correspondence: T, including James M. Taylor congratulates Alderman upon his marriage (February 2, 1904); Alderman to Dr. W.S. Thayer protesting the German deportation of Belgians for labor (December 19, 1916); Alderman to A.F. Thomas concerning the charges leveled against Senator Martin by Mr. Jones during the current election (August 23, 1911); Ashley H. Thorndike asking to include one of Alderman's after dinner speeches in one volume of Modern Eloquence (December 13, 1922); Alderman to Walter Tittle concerning his photographic "fish tale" (1928); C.W. Toms; Walker D. Toy; Dr. E.L. Trudeau; the Reverend Beverley D. Tucker, Jr.; Henry St. George Tucker (1853-1932) urging Alderman to make the requested speech in Albany, New York (January 5, 1912); Robert B. Tunstall enclosing three typescript copies of letters from Woodrow Wilson to Tunstall (November 30, 1910) and two letters from Alderman to Tunstall about the University raising endowment funds (November 28, 1919 and April 22, 1921); and Alderman to Lyon G. Tyler, President of William and Mary, describing his meeting with Andrew Carnegie (April 21, 1905) (Box-folder 5:13)
  - 1905-1915 Correspondence: William Howard Taft (1857-1930), Alderman congratulates Taft on his election and asks for a future appointment to discuss ways Taft could "get hold constructively of Southern life" (November 30, 1908); Taft will consider Dr. Joseph A. Holmes for the Directorship of the Mines (May 17, 1910); and Taft lectures at the University of Virginia (January 10, February 1, July 24, 1915) originals transferred to Vault (Box-folder 5:14)
  - ca. 1912-1913 Correspondence: Katrina Trask (1853-1922), writer and co-founder with husband Spencer Trask of Yaddo, Saratoga Springs, New York, writes letter of sympathy and encouragement during Alderman's enforced stay at Saranac Lake, New York, due to tuberculosis (Box-folder 5:15)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence: Elbert Lee Trinkle (1876-1939), Governor of Virginia, states to Alderman that he "immortalized yourself" with his oration on Woodrow Wilson in the House of Representatives (December 16, 1924); a typed copy of a letter from Alderman to Trinkle while he was vacationing in the Karlsbad [Czechoslovakia] area of Europe mentions talking with President Masaryk about the problems of small states in Central Europe, the support Trinkle has given to the University of Virginia while in office, and includes a memorandum and a list of suggestions for the Governor concerning taxation and education needs (summer 1925); and a copy of a letter from Alderman stating the advances made by the University during the administration of Trinkle (November 16, 1925) (Box-folder 5:16)
  - 1904-1930 Correspondence: U through V, including Senator Oscar W. Underwood (November 1, 1911; October 15, 1923); Underwood and Underwood [Photographers]; unidentified editor of the The World, New York (March 30, 1928); Alderman to Samuel Untermyer (1858-1940) asking for a Centennial donation and explaining why the University would be a worthy recipient (April 12, 1921); Henry van Dyke declining to speak at the University (September 12, 1905); Augustus Van Wyck concerning educational development in Brooklyn, New York (February 12, 1904); two letters from Alderman to Joseph Lee Vaughan concerning his lecture before the first year English students in Cabell Hall on books he had read (October 18 and November 15, 1930); Alderman to Marion J. Verdery sending a suggestion for the Deems Memorial Fund (February 9, 1916); Alderman to E.K. Vietor disagreeing over their interpretation of recent European history since 1815 (February 18, 1915); and Oswald Garrison Villard (1872-1949) referring to his recent speech with bitterest disappointment (March 8, 1904) and to Woodrow Wilson with excitement (March 14, 1913) (Box-folder 5:17)
  - 1895-1930 Correspondence: W, including Alfred Moore Waddell praises Alderman's address on William Kooper (May 12, 1895); copy of letter from Alderman to Rector Cyrus Harding Walker about the need for matching appropriations in the General Assembly (January 20, 1926); Knox Polk Walker, Infantry, AEF (May 24, 1918); Belle Ward, the Hartridge School, Plainfield, New Jersey; H.C. Warmoth; T.Herbert Warren; Alderman to Mrs. George W. Watts concerning the death of her husband (April 11, 1921); Alexander Wilbourne Weddell; Alderman to James B. Wells concerning the place of Latin at the University of Virginia (May 25, 1908); Alderman to Lt. Governor Junius Edgar West (1866-1947) about the progress of North Carolina and the need for Virginia to keep pace (December 6, 1922); Benjamin Ide Wheeler (1854 -1927) inviting Alderman to deliver the Charter Day address for 1903 (December 5, 1902); Andrew D. White; Edward Douglas White; William H. White, University Board of Visitors assuring Alderman of their concern during his recovery (November 29, 1912); George H. Whitten concerning Alderman's greeting to Murray and Miriam Boocock (October 15, 24, 25, 1930); Sir Frederick Whyte Christmas card (n.d.); Jane E. Whyte; John Langborne Williams (1831-1915) expressing his appreciation of Alderman's speech before the alumni on democracy (November 21, 1911); John Sharp Williams (1854-1932) unable to accept a speaking engagement (January 21, 1904) and gives his opinion of sectionalism versus nationalism in the life of the nation (January 14, 1905); Alderman to Lewis C. Williams urging him to put Stewart Bryan forth as the Chairman of the Finance Committee for the Association for Higher Education (March 14, 1927); Alderman to R. Gray Williams concerning his appreciation for the work of Governor Harry F. Byrd for education (March 23, 1926); Alderman to Mrs. Wilson concerning his trip to Europe (June 27, 1914); Colonel John M. Wilson, declining an invitation to the graduation exercises of the University of North Carolina (June 1, 1894); Alderman to R. Gray Williams giving his opinion of Governor Harry F. Byrd and the recent education bill (March 23, 1926); S.B. Woodfin; Alderman to Dr. C.G. Woodson concerning the "race problem" in America (February 3, 1921); and social letters from Dr. John A. Wyeth (Box-folder 5:18)
  - 1901, 1904 Correspondence: Booker T. Washington (1859-1915) writes about how encouraged he is by the work of men like Alderman, Dr. McIver, and Dr. Dabney in the field of Southern education, especially Alderman's suggestion in The Outlook concerning "the importance of having a sociological department endowed in several of the large white colleges in the South for the purpose of giving Southern white men the opportunity of making first hand investigations into the condition of the Negro." (December 4, 1901) and sends some statements prepared by Roscoe Conkling Bruce to answer some of the charges leveled in Governor [James K.] Vardaman's inaugural address and Alderman's questions concerning his statements about the Negro (January 27, 1904); Alderman's envelope with these materials is marked "The Negro and Crime Vardaman vs Washington" [1904]; originals transferred to Vault (Box-folder 5:19)
  - 1924-1930 Correspondence: Edith Bolling Galt Wilson (1872-1961), chiefly social notes to both Dr. and Mrs. Alderman, following the death of her husband, Woodrow Wilson, including her appreciation for their sympathy and Alderman's memorial speech before Congress, includes invitations, thank you notes, mentions of travel plans, such as a visit to Singapore and Japan (August 13, October 22, 1929); her interest in the preservation of Monticello (April 6, 1925); her trip to Venice, Italy (July 18, 1925); her pleasure at the success of the League of Nations over the Greek-Bulgarian war (November 2, 1925) (Box-folder 6:1)
  - 1931-1955, n.d. Correspondence: Edith Bolling Galt Wilson (1872-1961), continues the exchange of friendship almost to the end of the lives of Bessie Alderman and Edith Wilson, but number of items between them sharply reduce after the death of Edwin Alderman; mentions her trip to Poland as the guest of its President and where a monument to Woodrow Wilson will be dedicated (June 4, 1931) (Box-folder 6:2)
  - 1903-1924 Correspondence: Woodrow Wilson, includes Wilson's response to Alderman's question about the contribution of the South (January 29, 1903); Alderman tries to enlist the support of Wilson to the retirement application to the Carnegie Foundation of George T. Winston, President of North Carolina, A & M, and reviews Winston's contributions to education (April 21, 1908); Alderman's analysis of Virginia politics (November 25, 28, 1911); asks Alderman to have a talk with J.W. Fishburn of Charlottesville, a delegate from the Seventh Virginia District, to give him "a little tonic" (June 6, 1912); letters responding to suggestions of candidates for positions (March 17, 26, April 14, August 26, 1913; January 13, 1916; January 12, 25, 1917); legislation concerning the purchase of Monticello (March 1, 1915); appointment of Alderman to the International Commission for peace between Russia and the United States (William Jennings Bryan, May 8, 1915; June 1, 1915; and Robert Lansing, June 14, 1915); congratulations on Wilson's election (November 11, December 2, 1916); appointment of Alderman to the Board of Visitors, United States Naval Academy (January 30, 1917); Alderman praises Wilson's message to Congress defining United States war aims (January 11, 14, 1918) and his message to Congress at the conclusion of the War (December 14, 1918); opposes the resignation of Dr. Thomas Walker Page as Chairman of the United States Tariff Commission (March 6, 8, April 23, 28, 1920); the Honorary National Committee appointed in connection with the Centennial celebration of the University of Virginia (October 22, 1920); article by G. Lowes Dickinson in the Atlantic Monthly discussing Wilson (February 2, 1921); the Centennial celebration and one letter also mentioning the Woodrow Wilson portrait gift (April 19, 20, 30, December 29, 1921); Wilson recommends Stockton Axson for English literature professor (February 18, March 6, 1922); and notice of Woodrow Wilson's death to faculty and students (February 5, 1924); originals transferred to the Vault (Box-folder 6:3)
  - 1891-1914 Correspondence: George T. Winston (1852-1932), includes sympathy upon the death of Alderman's son (July 3, 1891); his opinion of the contributions of the South to American life (January 31, 1903); describes his own health (forced to retire on a Carnegie Pension due to ill health in 1908) and how much more he has learned and enjoyed life since his retirement from the world of education and the necessity of employing the theory of evolution in education (January 20, 1914) (Box-folder 6:4)
    Subseries B: Topical Correspondence
    - 1903 January-March Correspondence responding to Alderman's question "What influence Southern men and Southern principles have had on the development of the national character?" possibly for a speech. Correspondents, in alphabetical order, include: Charles F. Adams; Henry Adams; Felix Adler; Edward Porter Alexander; Charles J. Bonaparte; William Garrott Brown; George Washington Cable; Winston Churchill (1871-1947), American novelist; Senator John W. Daniel; Charles B. Galloway (1849-1909); Walter B. Hill; Senator George F. Hoar; Grace King; Alexander K. McClure; Ashton Phelps; Thomas R. Price; Carl Schurz (1829-1906); Bishop Davis Sessums; N.S. Shaler; Albert Shaw; Hoke Smith; William M. Smith; Bishop John Lancaster Spalding; Hannis Taylor; William Peterfield Trent; Frederick J. Turner; Alfred M. Waddell; Thomas E. Watson; C.B. Wilmer; John S. Wise; and Owen Wister (Box-folder 6:5)
    - 1900-1901 Correspondence concerning Alderman's Tenure as President of Tulane University, chiefly with the alumni, faculty and deans of Tulane, including: Brown Ayres, Robert Bingham, R.K. Bruff, John Williamson Caldwell, Thomas Carter, Stanford Emerson Chaille, William Henry P. Creighton, John Hanno Deiler, J.H. Dillard, Brandt Van Blarcom Dixon, Charles E. Fenner, John R. Ficklen, Alcee Fortier, Grace King, Monte Lemann, J.W. Pearce, J.H. Rapp, Edward Richtor, William D. Rogers, Robert Sharp, W.B. Smith, George H. Terriberry, L.W. Wilkinson, William Woodward (Box-folder 6:6)
    - 1896 July-August 7 Correspondence congratulating Alderman upon his selection and inauguration as President of the University of North Carolina (Box-folder 6:7)
    - 1896 August 8-Dec Correspondence congratulating Alderman upon his selection and inauguration as President of the University of North Carolina (Box-folder 6:8)
    - 1897, n.d. Correspondence congratulating Alderman upon his selection and inauguration as President of the University of North Carolina (Box-folder 6:9)
  - 1904 Correspondence congratulating Alderman upon his selection as President of the University of Virginia, and including telegrams from Rector Charles P. Jones, J.M. Page, Chairman of the Faculty, and John S. Patton, on behalf of the General Alumni Association o f the University, with Alderman's replies, informing him of his election, arranged alphabetically by correspondent (Box-folder 7:1)
  - 1929-1930 Correspondence concerning the Bronze Bust of Alderman created by Sergei Konenkov, also includes speeches of acceptance by Robert B. Tunstall and William M. Thornton (June 9, 1930) and news clippings (Box-folder 7:2)
  - 1928 Correspondence concerning the charges made against the University of Virginia by the Reverend David Hepburn, Superintendent of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League, and the response of Alderman in a printed Open Letter to Governor Harry Flood Byrd and prohibition; for related news clippings see folder in Box 13(1 of 2 folders) (Box-folder 7:3)
  - 1928 Correspondence concerning the charges made against the University of Virginia by the Reverend David Hepburn, Superintendent of the Virginia Anti-Saloon League, and the response of Alderman in a printed Open Letter to Governor Harry Flood Byrd and prohibition; for related news clippings see folder in Box 13 (2 of 2 folders) (Box-folder 7:4)
  - 1903-1930 January Correspondence - Invitations and Requests (Box-folder 7:5)
  - 1930 February-May Correspondence - Invitations and Requests (Box-folder 7:6)
  - 1930 June-September Correspondence - Invitations and Requests (Box-folder 7:7)
  - 1930 October-December Correspondence - Invitations and Requests (Box-folder 8:1)
  - 1931-1932 Correspondence - Invitations and Requests (Box-folder 8:2)
  - 1931 April 30-May1 Correspondence - Letters of Condolence upon the Death of Edwin A. Alderman to Mrs. Alderman, for each day, alphabetically arranged by correspondent (Box-folder 8:3)
  - 1931 May 2-7 Correspondence - Letters of Condolence upon the Death of Edwin A. Alderman to Mrs. Alderman, for each day, alphabetically arranged by correspondent (Box-folder 8:4)
  - 1931 May 8-30 Correspondence - Letters of Condolence upon the Death of Edwin A. Alderman to Mrs. Alderman, for each day, alphabetically arranged by correspondent (Box-folder 8:5)
  - 1931 June-1932 Correspondence - Letters of Condolence upon the Death of Edwin A. Alderman to Mrs. Alderman, on each day, alphabetically arranged by correspondent, including a letter from Clarence N. Goodwin about talking with Alderman on the train during his last hours, January 19, 1932; this folder also contains typed lists of out-of-town callers, flower lists, letters to Mrs. Alderman, and telegrams sent to Mrs. Alderman (Box-folder 8:6)
  - 1930-1931 Correspondence concerning the Order of Crown of Italy given to President Edwin A. Alderman and Professor William A. Lambeth (Box-folder 8:7)
  - 1900-1931 Correspondence concerning Speeches and Articles by Alderman (Box-folder 9:1)
  - 1928 Correspondence concerning Speeches and Articles by Alderman - American Bankers Association and Related Materials (Box-folder 9:2)